Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 3: Congenital Genitourinary Abnormalities.
Genitourinary Tract Development Sexual Differentiation Disorders Of Sex Development Bladder And Perineal Abnormalities MÜLLERIAN ABNORMALITIES Uterine Flexion.
References.
In females, the external genitalia, gonads, and müllerian ducts each derive from different primordia and in close association with the urinary tract and hindgut.
Abnormal embryogenesis can lead to reproductive organs that predispose to infertility, subfertility, miscarriage, or preterm delivery.
Genitourinary Tract Development.
# Urinary System.
Between the 3rd and 5th gestational weeks, an elevation of intermediate mesoderm on each side of the fetus begins to develop into the urogenital tract.
This urogenital ridge divides into the genital ridge, destined to become the gonads, and into the nephrogenic ridge .
Each nephrogenic ridge produces a mesonephros (mesonephric kidney).
Recall that evolution of the renal system passes sequentially from the mesonephric stage to reach the permanent metanephric system (de Bakker, 2019; Upadhyay, 2014).
Each nephrogenic ridge also gives rise to a mesonephric duct, also termed wolffian duct, and to a paramesonephric duct, also called müllerian duct.
Figure 3-1.
A. Cross-section of an embryo at 4 to 6 weeks.
B. Primordial germ cells migrate (arrows) from the yolk sac to the area of germinal epithelium, within the genital ridge.
C. Development of gonad.
Also, migration of sympathetic cells from the spinal ganglia to a region above the developing kidney.
The early urinary tract develops from the mesonephric ducts (Fig. 3-2A).
Between the 4th and 5th weeks, each mesonephric duct gives rise to a ureteric bud, which grows cephalad (Fig. 3-2B).
As each bud lengthens, it induces differentiation of the metanephros, which will become the final kidney (Fig. 3-2C) .
The metanephros ascends to its final position by the 9th week because of disproportionate growth of the embryo’s caudal region .
Each ureteric bud also gives rise to an elongation that becomes the metanephric duct or future ureter.
Figure 3-2.
Embryonic development of the female genitourinary tract (A–F).
Reproduced with permission from Shatzkes DR, Haller JO, Velcek FT: Imaging of uterovaginal anomalies in the pediatric patient, Urol Radiol 1991;13(1):58–66.
The cloaca begins as a common opening for the embryonic urinary, genital, and alimentary tracts .
By the 7th week, it is divided by the urorectal septum to create the hindgut and the urogenital sinus (Fig. 3-2D) .
The urogenital sinus is considered in three parts: (1) the cephalad or vesicle portion, which forms the urinary bladder; (2) the middle or pelvic portion, which creates the female urethra; and (3) the caudal or phallic part, which gives rise to the distal vagina and to the greater vestibular (Bartholin) and paraurethral glands.
Near the end of the first trimester, each mesonephros degenerates, and without testosterone, the mesonephric ducts regress as well.
The ureterovesical junction forms from incorporation of the metanephric ducts into the bladder at the trigone.
Abnormalities of this process lead to obstruction and vesicoureteral reflux .
# Genital Tract.
The fallopian tubes, uterus, and upper vagina derive from the müllerian ducts (see Fig. 3-2B).
Linear spatial development of these organs along the duct length is guided by several genes and notably by Hox genes (Du, 2004; Jacquinet, 2016).
These ducts extend downward and then turn medially to meet and fuse together in the midline.
The uterus is formed by this union of the two müllerian ducts at approximately the 10th week (Fig. 3-2E) .
Fusion to create the uterus begins in the middle and then extends both caudally and cephalad.
With cellular proliferation at the upper portion, a thick wedge of tissue creates the characteristic piriform uterine shape.
At the same time, dissolution of cells at the lower pole forms the first uterine cavity (Fig. 3-2F).
As the upper wedge-shaped septum is slowly reabsorbed, the final uterine cavity is usually formed by the 20th week
If the two müllerian ducts fail to fuse, two separate uterine horns remain.
In contrast, resorption failure of the common tissue between them results in various degrees of persistent uterine septum.
As the distal end of the fused müllerian ducts contacts the urogenital sinus, this induces endodermal outgrowths from the sinus, which are termed the sinovaginal bulbs.
These bulbs proliferate and fuse to form the vaginal plate, which later resorbs to form the vaginal lumen.
Vaginal canalization is generally completed by the 20th week .
However, the lumen remains separated from the urogenital sinus by the hymeneal membrane.
This membrane further degenerates to leave only the hymeneal ring.
The close association of the mesonephric (wolffian) and paramesonephric (müllerian) ducts explains the potential to see simultaneous abnormalities in their end organs.
Nearly half of females with uterovaginal malformations have associated urinary tract defects, and this association is explored later (p. 40) (Kenney, 1984; Semmens, 1962).
With müllerian anomalies, ovaries are functionally normal but have a higher incidence of anatomical maldescent into the pelvis .
As discussed, the mesonephric ducts usually degenerate in the female.
However, persistent remnants may become clinically apparent.
Mesonephric, that is wolffian, vestiges can persist as Gartner duct cysts.
These are typically located in the proximal anterolateral vaginal wall but may be found at other sites along the vaginal length.
Most cysts are asymptomatic and benign and usually do not require surgical excision or drainage.
Intraabdominal wolffian remnants in the female include a few blind tubules in the mesovarium—the epoöphoron—and similar ones adjacent to the uterus—paroöphoron (see Fig. 3-2F) .
The epoöphoron or paroöphoron may develop into clinically identifiable benign cysts in the adult.
# Gonads.
Because of separate gonadal and müllerian derivation, women with müllerian defects typically have functionally normal ovaries.
At approximately 4 weeks, gonads form from the genital ridge, also known as the gonadal ridge.
This ridge forms from the coelomic epithelium covering the medioventral surface of the mesonephros .
Recall that coelomic epithelium arises from mesoderm and invests the body cavity’s inner surface .
Next, strands of these epithelial cells extend into the underlying mesenchyme as the primary sex cords.
Another gonadal component is the primordial germ cell, the future oogonia.
By the 6th week, primordial germ cells have migrated from the yolk sac along the dorsal mesentery to enter the genital ridge mesenchyme (see Fig. 3-1) (Fujimoto, 1977; Hen, 2019).
The primordial germ cells are then incorporated into the primary sex cords.
In the 7th week, the sexes can be distinguished.
Testes are recognized during microscopic sectioning by their well-defined radiating testis cords, which derived from the primary sex cords.
These cords develop into the seminiferous tubules and rete testis.
The rete testis connects with small tubes arising off the mesonephric duct.
These small tubes become the efferent ducts that drain into the epididymis and then into the vas deferens, which are main mesonephric duct derivatives.
After the 8th week, gonads begin to differ grossly as well .
In the female embryo, the primary sex cords give rise to the medullary cords, which persist only for a short time.
The coelomic epithelium again proliferates into the underlying mesenchyme, and these strands are the cortical cords.
By the 16th week, the cortical cords begin to form isolated cell clusters called primordial follicles.
These follicles contain the oogonia, which derive from primordial germ cells, and a single surrounding layer of follicular cells, derived from the cortical cords.
Follicular cells are supporting nutrient cells.
By 8 months, the ovary has become a long, narrow, lobulated structure that is attached to the body wall by the mesovarium.
The coelomic epithelium has been separated by a band of connective tissue—the tunica albuginea— from the cortex.
At
this stage, the cortex contains follicles and is well defined from the inner medulla, which is composed of abundant blood vessels, lymphatic vessels, and nerve fibers.
# External Genitalia.
Early development of the external genitalia is similar in both sexes.
By 6 weeks’ gestation, three external protuberances have developed surrounding the cloacal membrane.
These are the left and right cloacal folds, which meet ventrally to form the genital tubercle (Fig. 3-3A).
With division of the cloacal membrane into anal and urogenital membranes in the early 7th week, the cloacal folds become the anal and urethral folds, respectively.
Lateral to the urethral folds, genital swellings arise, and these become the labioscrotal folds.
Between the urethral folds, the urogenital sinus extends onto the surface of the enlarging genital tubercle to form the urethral groove.
Late in week 7, the urogenital membrane ruptures, exposing the cavity of the urogenital sinus to amnionic fluid.
Figure 3-3.
Development of the external genitalia.
A. Indifferent stage.
B. Virilization of external genitalia.
C. Feminization.
The genital tubercle elongates to form the phallus in males and the clitoris in females.
Still, it is not possible to visually differentiate between male and female external genitalia until week 12.
In the male fetus, dihydrotestosterone (DHT) forms locally by the 5-α reduction of testosterone.
DHT prompts the anogenital distance to lengthen, the phallus to enlarge, and the labioscrotal folds to fuse and form the scrotum (see Fig. 33B).
In the female fetus, without DHT, the anogenital distance does not lengthen, and the labioscrotal and urethral folds do not fuse (see Fig. 3-3C).
The genital tubercle bends caudally to become the clitoris, and the urogenital sinus forms the vestibule of the vagina.
The labioscrotal folds create the labia majora, whereas the urethral folds persist as the labia minora.
Female external genitals are differentiated by 11 weeks, whereas male external genital differentiation is complete by 14 weeks.
To differentiate phenotypic gender early, first-trimester sonography relies on the angle of the genital tubercle off a horizontal line drawn parallel to the lumbosacral skin surface .
Specifically, male gender is assigned if the angle is >30°, and female gender if the angle is <10°.
Figure 3-4.
First-trimester transvaginal sonogram shows a male fetus, whose phallus lies at an angle that is ≥30 degrees above the horizontal.
The horizontal line aligns with the fetal lumbosacral skin.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Ashley Zink.
Sexual Differentiation.
Defining gender incorporates genetic gender, gonadal gender, and phenotypic gender.
Genetic gender—XX or XY—is established at fertilization.
However, for the first 6 weeks, male and female embryos are morphologically indistinguishable.
Gonadal gender is heralded by the differentiation of the primordial gonad into a testis or an ovary.
If a Y chromosome is present, the gonad begins developing into a testis.
Testis development is directed by the sexdetermining region (SRY) gene, located on the short arm of the Y chromosome .
In addition, testis development requires other autosomal genes that include SOX9, WT1, DAX1, WNT4, and NR5A1(SF1) .
Identified mutations in these and others are linked to disorders of sex development, described next.
The importance of the SRY gene is demonstrated in several paradoxical conditions.
For example, 46,XX phenotypic males can result from translocation of the Y chromosome fragment containing SRY to the X chromosome during meiosis of male germ cells .
Similarly, 46,XY individ-uals can appear phenotypically female if they carry a mutation in the SRY gene .
Last, phenotypic gender begins at 8 weeks’ gestation.
Before this, urogenital tract development in both sexes is homologous.
Thereafter, differentiation of the internal and external genitalia to the male phenotype is dependent on testicular function and response.
In its absence, female differentiation ensues irrespective of genetic gender .
Table 3-1.
Embryonic
Urogenital Structures and Their Adult Homologues In males, the Sertoli cells of the fetal testis secrete a protein called antimüllerian hormone (AMH), also named müllerian-inhibiting substance (MIS).
It acts locally as a paracrine factor to cause müllerian duct regression (Grinspon, 2020; Mäkelä, 2019).
Thus, it prevents development of the uterus, fallopian tube, and upper vagina.
Sertoli cells secrete AMH before differentiation of Leydig cells, which synthesize testosterone.
AMH is secreted as early as 7 weeks, and müllerian duct regression is completed by 9 to 10 weeks.
Because AMH acts locally near its site of formation, if a testis were absent on one side, the müllerian duct on that side would persist, and the uterine horn and fallopian tube would develop on that side.
Through stimulation initially by human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG), and later by fetal pituitary luteinizing hormone (LH), Leydig cells secrete testosterone.
This hormone acts directly on the wolffian duct to promote development of the vas deferens, epididymis, and seminal vesicles.
Testosterone also enters fetal blood and acts on the external genitalia.
In these tissues, testosterone is converted to 5α-DHT to cause virilization of the external genitalia.
Leydig cells also produce insulin-like factor 3, which prompts embryonic testes to descend by acting on the gubernaculum .
Disorders Of Sex Development.
# Definitions.
Abnormal sex development may involve the gonads, internal duct system, or external genitalia.
Current classification of disorders of sex development (DSDs) include: (1) sex chromosome DSDs, (2) 46,XY DSDs, and (3) 46,XX DSDs .
Rates vary depending on included entities and approximate 1 case in every 5000 births .
Table 3-2.
Disorders of Sex Development (DSD) Classification Other terms describe abnormal phenotypic findings.
First, some DSDs have abnormal, underdeveloped gonads, that is, gonadal dysgenesis.
With this, a poorly formed testis is called a dysgenetic testis.
A poorly formed ovary is a streak gonad.
Underdeveloped gonads ultimately fail, which creates low sex steroid hormone levels but elevated follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and LH levels.
A second term, ambiguous genitalia, describes genitalia that do not appear clearly male or female.
Abnormalities can include hypospadias, undescended testes, micropenis or enlarged clitoris, labial fusion, and labial mass.
Last, ovotesticular defines a rare state characterized by ovarian and testicular tissue in the same individual.
It was formerly termed true hermaphroditism.
In these cases, different gonad types can be paired.
Pair combinations may include a normal testis, a normal ovary, a streak gonad, a dysgenetic testis, or an ovotestis.
In the last, both ovarian and testicular elements are combined within the same gonad.
With ovotesticular cases, the internal ductal system structure depends on the type of ipsilateral gonad and its function.
Specifically, the amount of AMH and testosterone determines the degree to which the internal ductal system is retained or reabsorbed (p. 35).
With inadequate AMH, müllerian duct derivatives persist.
With inadequate testosterone, external genitalia are usually ambiguous and undermasculinized.
Ovotesticular development may be found in all three of the DSD categories, and each of these sections describes examples .
# Germ Cell Cancer.
This cancer can develop in dysgenetic gonads of patients bearing all or part of the Y chromosome.
On the Y chromosome, the gene for testis-specific protein Y (TSPY) is one putative cancer-predisposing gene.
Other risks include disturbed gonadal development, delayed germ cell maturation, and presence of a gonadoblastoma .
The last is a benign tumor that contains germ cells and immature granulosa cells .
Germ cell cancer (GCC) risk varies among DSD types, but for some, gonadectomy may be recommended by a multispecialty DSD team .
Early surgery benefits those with higher GCC risk and those in whom gonadal hormones may run counter to preferred pubertal development for the individual’s chosen gender
identity.
Later surgery may benefit those with low GCC risk and in whom gonadal hormones would advance desired pubertal development (van der Zwan, 2015).
In addition to dysgenetic gonads, undescended testes also have higher GCC rates .
Instead of gonadectomy, orchiopexy, which translocates and fixes a testis into the scrotum, may be protective (Radmayr, 2016; Walsh, 2007).
# Sex Chromosome DSD.
Cases in this first DSD category typically arise from an abnormal number of sex chromosomes, that is, sex chromosome aneuploidy (SCA).
The population rate approximates 1 case per 2500 births .
Discussed fully in Chapter 17 (p. 333), prenatal screening methods allow detection of aneuploidies, including SCAs .
Sonographically, a thick nuchal translucency or the presence of cystic hygromas is associated with an increased SCA risk (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020; Reiss, 2017).
Cell-free DNA present in the maternal blood is another common aneuploidy screening tool (Fig. 16-14, p. 328) (Huang, 2018; Vogel, 2019).
Its selection solely for gender identification and without a medical indication is not recommended by the American College of Medical Genetics and Genomics .
Still, with cell-free DNA use for other indications, antenatal detection of SCAs will likely rise.
Interpretation and management of findings is discussed in Chapter 17 (p. 335).
Advantageously, early recognition of sex chromosome DSD offers an opportunity for patient education.
Decisions to end or continue pregnancies are best guided by clinical geneticists.
For continued pregnancies, prenatal diagnosis allows early postnatal interventions .
Turner Syndrome This develops from de novo loss or severe structural abnormality of one X chromosome in a phenotypic female.
Most affected fetuses are spontaneously aborted.
However, 1 in 2000 female live births are affected .
In survivors with Turner syndrome, phenotype varies but nearly all affected patients have short stature.
Associated problems can include hypertension; cardiac abnormalities, especially aortic coarctation, bicuspid aortic valve, and QT-interval prolongation; and renal, skeletal, and otolaryngological anomalies.
A webbed posterior neck results from cystic hygromas.
Metabolic concerns are diabetes mellitus (DM), autoimmune thyroiditis, celiac disease, and elevated liver enzymes .
Two streak ovaries are typically found, and this syndrome is the most common form of gonadal dysgenesis that leads to primary ovarian insufficiency (POI).
POI is the depletion or dysfunction of ovarian follicles that leads to failing sex hormone production.
The uterus and vagina are normal and respond to prescribed hormones .
Despite eventual POI, women with Turner syndrome may conceive with assisted reproductive technologies (ART) and rarely spontaneously (Hovatta, 1999; Oktay, 2016).
In gravidas with Turner syndrome, cardiac morbidity stems from aortic dissection, aortic valve stenosis, and hypertension.
For this reason, maternal–fetal medicine preconceptional counseling and cardiologist evaluation is essential.
For aortic dissection, risk rises as the aortic diameter increases.
The ascending aortic size index (ASI), which is the aortic diameter divided by body surface area, better reflects risk because it accounts for short stature.
Conception should be avoided with an ASI >2.5 cm/m2 or with an ASI of 2.0 to 2.5 cm/m2 plus comorbid aortic dissection risk factors.
These include bicuspid aortic valve, transverse aortic arch elongation, aortic coarctation, and hypertension (Gravholt, 2017; Silberbach, 2018).
The American Society for Reproductive Medicine (2012) recommends against pregnancy with an ASI >2 cm.
Even without identified risk, aortic dissection can develop in pregnancy .
If conception is planned, preconceptional evaluation includes echocardiography, combined computed tomography plus cardiac magnetic resonance (CMR) imaging of the heart/aorta, 24-hour ambulatory blood pressure monitoring, exercise testing to reveal exercise-induced hypertension, and electrocardiogram .
Cardiac disorders may
require surveillance with serial echocardiograms.
This syndrome carries higher fetal rates of miscarriage, preterm birth, and small-for-gestational age.
Preeclampsia, gestational diabetes, and cholestasis of pregnancy are other maternal risks (Dotters-Katz, 2016a; Grewal, 2021).
Thus, baseline serum tests ideally assess renal, liver, and thyroid function and screen for DM .
These complications and cephalopelvic disproportion account for cesarean delivery rates of 40 to 80 percent in gravidas with Turner syndrome (Cadoret, 2018; Campens, 2021; Dotters-Katz, 2016a).
Klinefelter Syndrome This syndrome has an estimated prevalence of 1 case per 650 newborn males fetuses (Bojesen, 2003; Radicioni, 2010).
With chromosome complement of 47,XXY, these individuals tend to be tall, undervirilized males with gynecomastia and two small, firm testes.
They have greatly reduced fertility from hypogonadism due to gradual testicular failure.
These men are at increased risk for mediastinal germ cell tumors, osteoporosis, hypothyroidism, DM, breast cancer, cardiovascular abnormalities, and neurobehavioral disorders .
Affected fetuses may show a thick NT during first-trimester sonography .
Antepartum risks include preterm birth, cesarean delivery, small-for-gestational-age fetus, and neonatal death .
47,XXX and 47,XYY Karyotypes These rare karyotypes are found in 1 in 10,000 newborn females and 2 in 10,000 newborn males, respectively .
Sonographically, fetuses with either karyotype may show a thick NT and fetal-growth restriction .
Phenotypic range is wide, but both may be taller, show subtle facial and skeletal dysmorphisms, and display neurobehavioral problems such as autism spectrum and attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorders (Bardsley, 2013; Urbanus, 2020; Widby 2016).
Hormone levels and fertility are unaffected in most, although POI and semen abnormalities may be seen, respectively.
Sex Chromosomal Ovotesticular DSD In the sex chromosome DSD group, ovotesticular DSD may arise from a 46,XX/46,XY karyotype.
Here, an ovary, testis, or ovotestis may be paired.
For others, ovotesticular DSD arises from a chromosomal mosaic such as 45,X/46,XY.
With this karyotype, mixed gonadal dysgenesis shows a streak gonad on one side and either a dysgenetic testis or normal testis on the other.
For this reason, phenotypic gender varies widely.
# 46,XY DSD.
Insufficient androgen exposure of a fetus destined to be a male leads to 46,XY DSD—formerly called male pseudohermaphroditism.
Testes are often present, and the uterus is generally absent due to the normal action of AMH.
These individuals are usually sterile from abnormal spermatogenesis and a small phallus that is inadequate for coitus.
Described next, the etiology of 46,XY DSD may stem from abnormal testis development or from abnormal androgen production or action .
Rarely, 46,XY DSD may be part of another metabolic syndrome that alters structural development, such as Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome .
46,XY Gonadal Dysgenesis This spectrum of abnormal gonad underdevelopment includes complete, partial, or mixed 46,XY gonadal dysgenesis.
These are defined by karyotype and by the amount of abnormal testicular tissue.
Because of the potential for GCC, gonadectomy is often recommended (p. 36).
Of these, complete gonadal dysgenesis results from a mutation in the SRY gene or in other genes with testis-determining effects .
Swyer syndrome reflects SRY defects, whereas Frasier and Denys-Drash syndromes have WT1 mutations.
With both mutations, underdeveloped dysgenetic gonads fail to produce androgens or AMH, which results a normal prepubertal female phenotype and a normal müllerian system.
Partial gonadal dysgenesis defines those with gonad development intermediate between normal and dysgenetic testes.
Depending on percentages, wolffian and müllerian structures and genital ambiguity are variably expressed.
Mixed gonadal dysgenesis is one type of ovotesticular DSD.
As discussed in the last section, one gonad is streak, and the other is a normal testis or a dysgenetic testis.
The phenotype is wide ranging.
Last, testicular regression can follow initial testis development .
The phenotypic spectrum is broad and depends on the timing of testis failure.
Abnormal Androgen Production or Action Some cases of 46,XY DSD stem from abnormalities in: (1) testosterone biosynthesis, (2) LH-receptor function, (3) AMH function, or (4) androgenreceptor action.
First, the sex-steroid biosynthesis pathway can suffer enzymatic defects that block testosterone production.
Depending on blockade timing and degree, undervirilized males or phenotypic females may result.
In contrast to these central enzymatic defects, peripheral defects can be causative.
Namely, abnormal action of 5α-reductase type 2 enzyme impairs conversion of testosterone to DHT and blunts virilization.
Second, hCG/LH receptor abnormalities within the testes can lead to Leydig cell hypoplasia and decreased testosterone production.
In contrast, disorders of AMH and AMH receptors result in persistent müllerian duct syndrome (PMDS).
These patients appear as males but have a persistent uterus and fallopian tubes due to failed AMH action.
Last, the androgen receptor may be defective and result in androgeninsensitivity syndrome (AIS).
Resistance to androgens may be incomplete and result in varying degrees of virilization and genital ambiguity.
Milder forms may lead to poorly virilized men with severe male-factor infertility.
Those with complete androgen-insensitivity syndrome (CAIS) are phenotypically normal females.
Girls often present at puberty with primary amenorrhea.
External genitalia appear normal; pubic and axillary hair are scant or absent; the vagina is markedly shortened; and the uterus and fallopian tubes are absent.
However, these individuals develop breasts during puberty due to conversion of androgen to estrogen.
Testes may be palpable in the labia or groin or may lie intraabdominally.
Traditionally, testes are removed.
However, women with AIS have a low risk of GCC, and retention until after puberty allows hormone-mediated breast and bone mass development.
Despite hormone replacement after ultimate gonadectomy, many individuals describe hormone-related mood imbalance.
New cancersurveillance protocols may allow gonad retention (Cools, 2017; Weidler, 2019).
# 46,XX DSD.
This DSD group may stem from abnormal ovarian development or from excess androgen exposure.
Abnormal Ovarian Development Disorders of ovarian development in those with a 46,XX complement include: (1) gonadal dysgenesis, (2) testicular DSD, and (3) ovotesticular DSD.
With 46,XX gonadal dysgenesis, similar to Turner syndrome, streak gonads develop.
These lead to hypogonadism, prepubertal normal female genitalia, and normal müllerian structures.
However, other Turner stigmata are absent.
With 46,XX testicular DSD, several genetic mutations lead to testis-like formation.
Most commonly, defects stem from SRY translocation onto one paternal X chromosome.
Less often, other genes with testis-determining effects are activated.
Regardless, AMH prompts müllerian system regression, and androgens promote wolffian system development and external genitalia masculinization.
Spermatogenesis, however, is absent because needed genes on the long arm of the Y chromosome are lacking.
These persons are not usually diagnosed until puberty or during infertility evaluation.
With 46,XX ovotesticular DSD, individuals possess a unilateral ovotestis with a contralateral ovary or testis, or bilateral ovotestes.
An overexpression of SOX genes, which are testis promoting, or deficient ovarian promoting genes are implicated .
Phenotypic findings depend on the degree of androgen exposure.
Androgen Excess Discordance between female gonadal sex and phenotypically masculine external genitalia may also result from excessive fetal androgen exposure.
The prior term was female pseudohermaphroditism.
In affected individuals, the ovaries and female internal ductal structures such as the uterus, cervix, and upper vagina develop.
Thus, patients are potentially fertile.
The external genitalia, however, are variably virilized depending on the
amount and timing of androgen exposure.
The embryonic clitoris, labioscrotal folds, and urogenital sinus are commonly affected by elevated androgen levels.
Virilization may range from modest clitoromegaly to posterior labial fusion and a phallus with a penile urethra.
Degrees of virilization can be described by the Prader score, which ranges from 0 for a normal-appearing female to 5 for a normal, virilized male.
The external genitalia score is another and similarly ranges from 0 to 12, respectively (Ahmed, 2000; van der Straaten, 2020).
Fetal, placental, or maternal sources can provide the excessive androgen levels.
Maternally derived androgen excess may come from virilizing ovarian tumors such as luteoma and Sertoli-Leydig cell tumor or from virilizing adrenal tumors.
Fortunately, these neoplasms infrequently cause fetal effects because of the placental syncytiotrophoblast’s tremendous ability to convert C19 steroids—androstenedione and testosterone—into estradiol via the enzyme aromatase .
As another source, drugs such as testosterone, danazol, and other androgen derivatives may virilize.
Of fetal sources, exposure can arise from fetal congenital adrenal hyperplasia (CAH).
This stems from a fetal enzyme deficiency in the steroidogenic pathway and leads to androgen accumulation.
Most cases have a 21-hydroxylase deficiency.
Rarely, others involve deficient 3βhydroxysteroid dehydrogenase, 17α-hydroxylase, cholesterol side-chain cleavage enzyme, P450 oxidoreductase, or 11β-hydroxylase (El-Maouche, 2017; Narasimhan, 2019).
CAH is a frequent cause of virilization, and its approximate incidence in the United States is 1 case in 18,000 live births (Chan, 2013; Pearce, 2016).
With CAH, phenotypes depend on the enzyme defect’s location in the steroidogenic pathway and its severity .
Classically, deficient enzymes block corticosteroid production, which feeds back to raise adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) levels.
This prompts increased levels of precursors, which detour into pathways that generate androgens.
With severe deficiency, affected newborns also have blocked aldosterone production that leads to life-threatening salt wasting.
This is typified by hyponatremia, hyperkalemia, metabolic acidosis, and hypovolemia .
Other mutations may prompt fetal virilization alone .
The mildest abnormalities present later and are described as “nonclassic,” “late-onset,” or “adult-onset” CAH.
In these patients, adrenal axis activation at puberty increases steroidogenesis and unmasks mild enzymatic deficiency.
Excess androgen provides negative feedback to gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) receptors in the hypothalamus.
These patients often have hirsutism, acne, and anovulation.
Thus, late-onset CAH may mimic polycystic ovarian syndrome .
In some instances, CAH can be diagnosed antenatally.
Early maternal dexamethasone therapy can dampen androgen excess to minimize virilization .
Cell-free DNA can identify fetal gonadal gender.
If Ychromosome cell-free DNA is identified, androgens will not harm the male fetus and maternal dexamethasone treatment can be stopped .
Of rare placental sources, placental aromatase deficiency from a fetal CYP19 gene mutation causes accumulation of placental androgen and underproduction of placental estrogens .
Consequently, both the mother and the 46,XX fetus are virilized.
# Gender Assignment.
Delivery of a newborn with a DSD is a potential medical emergency and can also create possible long-lasting psychosexual and social ramifications for the individual and family.
Ideally, once the affected neonate is stable, parents are encouraged to hold the child.
The newborn is referred to as “your baby,” and suggested terms include “phallus,” “gonads,” “folds,” and “urogenital sinus” to reference underdeveloped structures.
An obstetrician explains that the genitalia are incompletely formed and emphasizes the situation’s seriousness and need for rapid consultation and laboratory testing.
Because similar or identical phenotypes may have several etiologies, identification of a
specific DSD may require several diagnostic tools .
Relevant historical questions seek prior obstetrical outcomes, medication inventory, consanguinity, germane antenatal testing and sonography results, and family history of genetic or structural anomalies.
Signs of maternal hyperandrogenism are sought.
Neonatal physical examination evaluates: (1) ability to palpate gonads in the labioscrotal or inguinal regions, (2) ability to palpate uterus during rectal examination, (3) phallus size, (4) other syndromic features, and (5) genitalia pigmentation, which derives from increased melanocyte-stimulating hormone levels that can accompany ACTH secretion.
The newborn metabolic condition is assessed, and hyperkalemia, hyponatremia, and hypoglycemia may indicate CAH.
Other neonatal tests include genetic studies, hormone measurements, imaging, and in some cases endoscopic, laparoscopic, and gonadal biopsy.
Sonography or magnetic resonance (MR) imaging can help identify müllerian/wolffian structures, gonad location, and associated malformations such as renal anomalies.
Bladder And Perineal Abnormalities.
During embryo formation, a bilaminar cloacal membrane lies at the caudal end of the germinal disc and forms the infraumbilical abdominal wall.
Normally, an ingrowth of mesoderm between the ectodermal and endodermal layers leads to formation of the lower abdominal musculature and pelvic bones.
Without this reinforcement, the cloacal membrane may prematurely rupture.
Depending on the infraumbilical defect’s extent, cloacal exstrophy, bladder exstrophy, or epispadias may result, and all are rare.
Cloacal exstrophy, also known as the omphalocele, bladder exstrophy, imperforate anus, spina bifida (OEIS) complex, affects approximately 1 in 300,000 live births (Keppler-Noreuil, 2007; Woo, 2010).
With bladder exstrophy, the bladder lies outside the abdomen, is open, drains directly into amnionic fluid, and thus does not fill.
Sonography in the first trimester may show a thin-walled, lower-abdominal cystic structure and a thick NT (Mallmann, 2014; Tonni, 2011).
During second-trimester scans, findings are a midline, infraumbilical, anterior-abdominal-wall defect, failure to see the bladder, and associated OEIS defects .
Prenatal karyotyping is recommended.
Delivery route is usually dictated by the associated spina bifida defect.
Postnatal repair is complex, and individuals may struggle with urinary and fecal incontinence and the challenges of neonatal gender assignment .
With bladder exstrophy, associated findings often include abnormal external genitalia and a widened symphysis pubis.
At the same time, however, the uterus, fallopian tubes, and ovaries are typically normal except for occasional müllerian duct fusion defects.
Although often not identified in affected fetuses, sonographic indicators are inability to see the bladder, solid mass between the umbilical arteries, low umbilical insertion into the abdomen, divergent pubic rami, normal amnionic fluid volume, and in males, a small penis with anteriorly displaced scrotum .
The differential diagnosis includes bladder exstrophy or agenesis, bilateral ectopic ureters, patent urachus, cloacal exstrophy, and simple nonvisualization of the bladder.
MR imaging may be a helpful adjunct .
Fetal karyotyping is considered if genitalia are ambiguous.
For an affected fetus, the prenatal course is typically routine, and cesarean delivery is reserved for obstetrical indications.
For a gravida with bladder exstrophy herself, pregnancy is associated with greater risk for antepartum pyelonephritis, urinary retention, ureteral obstruction, pelvic organ prolapse, miscarriage, preterm birth, and breech presentation.
The American Urological Association has published management guidelines for pregnancy .
Due to the extensive adhesions from prior repair and altered anatomy typically encountered, some recommend planned early cesarean delivery at a tertiary center (Deans, 2012; Greenwell, 2003).
Dy and coworkers (2015) described using paramedian abdominal wall and vertical uterine incisions.
Epispadias
without bladder exstrophy is rare and develops in association with other anomalies such as a widened, patulous urethra; absent or bifid clitoris; nonfused labial folds; and flattened mons pubis.
Vertebral abnormalities and pubic symphysis diathesis are also common.
Clitoral anomalies are rare.
One is clitoral duplication or bifid clitoris, which usually develops in association with bladder exstrophy or epispadias.
With female phallic urethra, the urethra opens at the clitoral tip.
Last, clitoromegaly noted at birth suggests fetal exposure to excessive androgens (p. 38).
Without a DSD, idiopathic congenital clitoromegaly in females born extremely premature is rare but well-recognized, and observation is recommended .
As noted, the hymen marks the embryological boundary between structures derived from the müllerian and urogenital sinus.
Hymeneal anomalies include imperforate, microperforate, cribriform (sievelike), navicular (boat-shaped), and septate hymens.
They result from failure of the inferior end of the vaginal plate—the hymeneal membrane—to canalize.
Rarely, with an imperforate hymen, secretions may markedly accumulate in the fetal uterus and vagina, that is, hydrometrocolpos (HMC).
Most cases of HMC are asymptomatic and resolve postnatally as mucus is reabsorbed and estrogen levels decline.
Rarely, perinatal urinary tract obstruction results from mass effect and is relieved with cruciate incision of the hymen .
Fetal HMC sonographically appears as a cystic mass behind the bladder.
The differential diagnosis includes reproductive tract outlet obstruction of the hymen, vagina, or cervix; ureterocele; megacystis; ovarian, urachal, or mesenteric cyst; anterior meningocele; bowel or bladder duplications; and urogenital sinus or cloacal dysgenesis.
Rare associated syndromes are McKusick-Kaufman, Ellis-van Creveld, or Bardet-Biedl syndromes .
MÜLLERIAN ABNORMALITIES Four principal abnormalities arise from defective müllerian duct embryological steps: (1) agenesis of both ducts, either focally or along the entire duct length; (2) unilateral maturation of one müllerian duct with incomplete or absent development of the opposite side; (3) absent or faulty midline fusion of the ducts; or (4) defective canalization.
Various classifications have been proposed, and Table 3-3 shows the one from the American Fertility Society (1988).
This classification system is the most widely used, although several others have been created (Grimbizis, 2013, 2016; Ludwin, 2018b).
Table 3-3.
Classification of Müllerian Anomalies A müllerian anomaly is suspected if a vaginal septum, blind-ending vagina, or duplicated cervix is found.
Amenorrhea may be an initial complaint for those with agenesis of a müllerian component.
In those with outlet obstruction but functioning endometrium, pelvic pain may arise from occult blood that accumulates and distends the vagina, uterus, or fallopian tubes (Kapczuk, 2018; Patel, 2016).
Endometriosis and its associated dysmenorrhea, dyspareunia, and chronic pain are also frequent with outlet obstruction .
# Comorbid Renal Anomalies.
Renal anomalies most frequently accompany unicornuate uterus, uterine didelphys, and anomalies with an ipsilateral obstructive vaginal septum.
Less often, partial bicornuate, and partial septate uteri are associated .
When müllerian anomalies are identified, the urinary system can be evaluated with sonography, MR imaging, or intravenous pyelography .
The last two are advantageous because ureteral anatomy can be affected too.
An absent unilateral kidney is the most common finding.
On the other hand, if renal agenesis is found first, reproductive-tract imaging in early puberty may help identify müllerian anomalies early .
# Müllerian Agenesis (Class I).
Class I segmental defects are caused by müllerian hypoplasia or agenesis as shown in Figure 3-5 .
These developmental defects can affect the vagina, cervix, uterus, or fallopian tubes and may be isolated or may coexist with other müllerian anomalies.
Study Newer classification Figure 3-5.
Classification of müllerian
anomalies.
DES = diethylstilbestrol.
# Vaginal Abnormalities.
Of these, vaginal agenesis is the most profound and may be isolated or associated with other müllerian anomalies.
One example is the MayerRokitansky-Küster-Hauser (MRKH) syndrome, in which upper vaginal agenesis is typically associated with uterine hypoplasia or agenesis.
Less often, this syndrome also displays additional abnormalities and is known by the acronym MURCS (müllerian duct aplasia, renal aplasia, and cervicothoracic somite dysplasia) .
The obstetrical significance of vaginal anomalies depends greatly on the degree of obstruction.
Complete vaginal agenesis, unless corrected surgically, precludes pregnancy by vaginal intercourse.
With MRKH syndrome, a functional vagina can be created, but uterine agenesis proscribes childbearing.
In these women, however, ova can be retrieved for in vitro fertilization (IVF) and carriage by a surrogate mother .
Uterine transplantation is experimental but holds promise for these women (Johannesson, 2021; Jones, 2019).
Of other vaginal anomalies, congenital septa may form longitudinally or transversely, and each can arise from a fusion or resorption defect.
A longitudinal septum divides the vagina into right and left portions.
It may be complete and extend the entire vaginal length.
A partial septum usually forms high in the vagina but may develop at lower levels.
These septa are often associated with other müllerian anomalies .
During examination, the provider can usually guide a speculum up along one side of the septum.
Similarly, in labor, a complete longitudinal vaginal septum usually does not cause dystocia because the fetus can descend through one vaginal side, which dilates sufficiently.
An incomplete distal longitudinal septum, however, may interfere with descent, and antepartum resection is preferred .
Rarely, a woman with an incomplete distal longitudinal septum instead presents in labor.
During second-stage labor, this septum usually becomes attenuated by pressure from the fetal head.
After ensuring adequate analgesia, the attachment of the septum to the posterior vaginal wall is isolated between two clamps, transected, and ligated.
Following placenta delivery, the superior attachment is similarly isolated between clamps and transected, while carefully avoiding urethral injury.
A transverse septum poses an obstruction of variable thickness.
It may develop at any depth within the vagina, but most lie in the lower third .
Septa may or may not be perforate, and thus obstruction or infertility is possible.
In labor, perforate strictures may be mistaken for the upper limit of the vaginal vault, and the septal opening is misidentified as an undilated cervix .
If encountered during labor, and after the cervix has dilated completely, the head impinges on the septum and causes it to bulge downward.
If the septum does not spontaneously yield, slightly stretching its opening usually leads to further dilation.
Occasionally cruciate incisions that avoid the urethra and rectum are required to permit delivery (Blanton, 2003; Levin, 1963).
For a thick transverse septum, cesarean delivery may be necessary.
# Cervical Abnormalities.
Developmental abnormalities of the cervix include partial or complete agenesis, duplication, or a longitudinal dividing septum.
Complete agenesis is incompatible with pregnancy.
IVF with gestational surrogacy or with transmyometrial embryo transfer are options (Al-Jaroudi, 2011; Xu, 2009).
Instead, surgical correction by uterovaginal anastomosis successfully relieves outlet obstruction, but subsequent pregnancy and live birth rates are low .
Significant complications including deaths have accompanied such corrective surgery.
Some experts recommend hysterectomy for complete cervical agenesis and reserve reconstruction attempts for carefully selected patients with cervical dysgenesis (Roberts, 2011; Rock, 2010).
# Uterine Abnormalities.
From a large variety, a few of the more common congenital uterine malformations are shown in Table 3-3.
Assessing an accurate population prevalence is difficult
because the best diagnostic techniques are invasive.
The prevalence found with imaging ranges from 0.4 to 10 percent, and rates in women with recurrent miscarriage are significantly higher (Byrne, 2000; Dreisler, 2014; Saravelos, 2008).
In a general population, the most frequent finding is arcuate uterus, followed in descending order by septate, bicornuate, didelphic, and unicornuate classes .
As a group, these anomalies pose greater risk for miscarriage, malpresentation, preterm birth, and poor fetal growth (Chan, 2011a; Hua, 2011; Reichman, 2009).
Vaginal delivery is the preferred delivery route when feasible.
The cervix of the pregnancy-containing uterus or horn will typically dilate sufficiently.
Similarly, any proximal longitudinal septum will stretch to permit fetal descent.
Müllerian uterine anomalies may be discovered first during pelvic examination, cesarean delivery, tubal sterilization, or infertility evaluation.
Depending on clinical presentation, sonography, hysterosalpingography (HSG), MR imaging, laparoscopy, and hysteroscopy may also be diagnostic.
Each has limitations and thus may be combined to completely define anatomy.
If a müllerian anomaly is suspected, two-dimensional transvaginal sonography (2-D TVS) is initially performed in most clinical settings.
For this indication, the pooled accuracy for 2-D TVS is 90 to 92 percent .
Three-dimensional (3-D) TVS is more accurate than 2-D TVS because it provides uterine images from virtually any angle.
The diagnostic accuracy of 3-D TVS approaches 97 percent .
Thus, coronal images can be constructed, and these are essential in evaluating both internal and external uterine contours.
Both 2-D and 3-D TVS are suitable for use in pregnancy .
Figure 3-6.
A. Sagittal transvaginal sonogram shows a gestational sac surrounded by myometrium.
The gestational sac is not contiguous with the endocervical canal or with the main horn’s endometrium.
B. Here, two Pean clamps are placed across the vascular tissue bridge that separates the rudimentary horn (above) from the main uterine horn (below).
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Elaine L. Duryea.
Several studies reported good concordance between 3-D TVS and MR imaging of müllerian uterine anomalies (Deutch, 2008; Graupera, 2015).
MR imaging is often preferred for complex anatomy, especially cases for which corrective surgery is planned.
MR imaging provides clear delineation of both the internal and external uterine anatomy and has a reported accuracy of up to 100 percent for müllerian anomaly evaluation (Bermejo, 2010; Pellerito, 1992).
Moreover, secondary diagnoses such as renal or skeletal anomalies can be concurrently evaluated.
MR imaging without contrast is safe in pregnancy.
Saline infusion sonography (SIS) is a technique that instills fluid into the uterine cavity to distend and define cavity shape.
It improves delineation of internal uterine morphology.
However, SIS is contraindicated in pregnancy.
It requires a patent endometrial cavity.
In women undergoing fertility evaluation, HSG is usually selected for uterine cavity and tubal patency assessment.
It is contraindicated during pregnancy.
HSG poorly defines the external uterine contour and can delineate only patent cavities.
Described next, remember that some unicornuate rudimentary horns lack a cavity.
Also, outlet obstructions will preclude dye filling.
For infertility, hysteroscopy and/or laparoscopy plus chromotubation may help confirm or treat uterine cavity or tubal pathologies.
These also screen for endometriosis, which often coexists with both infertility and müllerian anomalies .
In pregnancy, laparoscopy is rarely used to diagnose müllerian defects, and hysteroscopy is contraindicated.
Unicornuate Uterus (Class II) General population estimates cite an incidence of 1 case in 4000 women .
In class II-D forms, only one uterine horn is present (see Fig. 3-5).
Instead, an underdeveloped rudimentary horn may be present.
The rudiment may or may not communicate with the dominant horn and may or may not contain an endometrium-lined cavity.
With
noncommunicating types, the rudiment may lie near the uterus or may lie anywhere along the embryological migration path of the paramesonephros.
This starts at the back and sweeps forward along the broad ligament.
This anomaly may be detected during fertility evaluation by HSG, but false-negative examinations stem from noncavitary or noncommunicating horns failing to fill with dye.
If this anomaly is suspected, 3-D TVS raises diagnostic accuracy, but again MR imaging may be preferred to define endometrium .
Importantly, 40 percent of affected women will have renal anomalies .
Main Horn.
Pregnancies developing in the main horn carry significant obstetrical risks.
These include first- and second-trimester miscarriage, malpresentation, fetal-growth restriction, fetal demise, prematurely ruptured membranes, and preterm delivery (Chan, 2011a; Hua, 2011; Reichman, 2009).
These risks theoretically stem from abnormal uterine blood flow, cervical insufficiency, and diminished cavity size and muscle mass .
The main unicornuate horn is indeed smaller than normal uterine lengths of 7- to 8-cm .
One small study of 140 nulligravidas found a median uterine length of 5 cm .
Those with lengths from the internal os to fundus <4.5 cm prior to pregnancy had higher preterm labor rates during subsequent pregnancy compared with longer hemiuteri.
Thus, a heightened awareness of potential complications is prudent.
However, specific surveillance for poor fetal growth or preterm labor is mainly guided by prior pregnancy outcomes.
Rudimentary Horn.
Ectopic pregnancy, correctly termed a cornual pregnancy, can develop within a remnant .
This risk includes noncommunicating cavitary rudiments, for which transperitoneal sperm migration permits ovum fertilization and pregnancy .
Although less common than other unicornuate pregnancy complications, rupture can create life-threatening hemorrhage.
Convergence of uterine and ovarian branches near the pregnancy and the commonly associated placenta accreta spectrum (PAS) explain this risk.
In a report of 70 such pregnancies, Rolen and associates (1966) found that most rudimentary uterine horn pregnancies ruptured prior to 20 weeks’ gestation.
Nahum (2002) reviewed the literature from 1900 to 1999 and identified 588 rudimentary horn pregnancies.
Half had uterine rupture, and 80 percent did so before the third trimester.
Of the total 588, the neonatal survival rate was only 6 percent.
First-trimester sonography allows an earlier diagnosis and rudiment excision before rupture.
The main horn shows an empty endometrium continuous with the cervical canal, and the interstitial portion of a fallopian tube is seen only on one side.
The rudimentary horn pregnancy displays: (1) no continuity between the cervical canal and gestational sac, (2) myometrium surrounding the gestation, (3) PAS-associated hypervascularity surrounding the gestational sac, and (4) a vascular pedicle connecting the main horn and the sac’s surrounding myometrium (Mavrelos, 2007; Tsafrir, 2005).
If necessary, 3-D TVS is an appropriate adjunct .
As seen in Figure 3-6.
the connecting pedicle can be broad and vascular.
Treatment is surgical and removes the rudimentary horn and in situ pregnancy.
The ipsilateral fallopian tube is also excised to avert future ectopic pregnancies (Dove, 2017; Worley, 2008).
Steps include sequential division of the uteroovarian ligament, mesosalpinx, round ligament, and pedicle to the main horn.
Ideally, the ovary is spared, but large pregnancies with a short uteroovarian ligament may prompt adnexectomy.
Surgical route is dictated by pregnancy size and laparoscopic capabilities.
In nonpregnant women, most unicornuate uteri are asymptomatic.
Those with a noncommunicating cavitary rudiment may present with outlet obstruction symptoms at puberty.
In this instance, comorbid endometriosis can club fimbria and obstruct tubal egress of blood.
In all cases, prophylactic excision of a cavitary rudiment is recommended to avoid pregnancy in an inadequately sized horn (Fedele, 2005; Rackow, 2007; Schneiderman, 2018).
Data
regarding subsequent pregnancy after excision are scarce.
In one series of eight women, all had a preterm cesarean delivery .
Uterine Didelphys (Class III) This anomaly arises from incomplete fusion that results in two entirely separate hemiuteri, two cervices, and usually two vaginas or a longitudinal vaginal septum (see Fig. 3-5).
Uterine didelphys may be isolated or part of a rare triad with an obstructed hemivagina and ipsilateral renal agenesis (OHVIRA), also known as Herlyn-Werner-Wunderlich syndrome .
Rarely diagnosed antenatally, it is considered in a fetus with renal agenesis and a cystic pelvic mass, which reflects hydrometrocolpos (p. 40) .
Fetal MR imaging aids diagnosis.
Uterine didelphys is suspected on pelvic examination by identification of a longitudinal vaginal septum and two cervices.
During HSG for fertility evaluation, contrast shows two separate endocervical canals.
These open into separate noncommunicating fusiform endometrial cavities that each ends with a solitary fallopian tube.
In women without fertility issues, 2- or 3-D TVS is a logical initial imaging tool, and separate divergent uterine horns with a large intervening fundal cleft are seen.
Endometrial cavities and two cervices are uniformly separate.
MR imaging can clarify cases lacking classic findings.
Adverse obstetrical outcomes associated with uterine didelphys are similar to but less frequent than those seen with unicornuate uterus.
Increased risks include miscarriage, preterm birth, and malpresentation (Chan, 2011a; Hua, 2011).
Metroplasty for either uterine didelphys or bicornuate uterus involves resection of intervening myometrium and fundal recombination .
These rarely performed surgeries are chosen for highly selected patients with otherwise unexplained recurrent miscarriage at later gestational ages.
After metroplasty, scheduled delivery prior to labor is prudent to avoid uterine rupture .
Bicornuate Uterus (Class IV) This fusion anomaly results in two hemiuteri.
As shown in Figure 3-5, the central myometrium runs either partially or completely to the cervix.
A complete bicornuate uterus may extend to the internal cervical os and have a single cervix (bicornuate unicollis) or reach the external os (bicornuate bicollis).
As with uterine didelphys, a coexistent longitudinal vaginal septum is common.
Radiological discrimination of a bicornuate uterus from a septate uterus can be challenging, and defining criteria vary.
This distinction, however, is important because septate uterus can be treated with hysteroscopic septal resection.
HSG or 2-D TVS may initially suggest an anomaly, but further distinction is provided by 3-D TVS or MR imaging.
With these, the intercornual angle, fundal contour, and a straight line drawn between the imaged tubal ostia serve as defining thresholds .
Figure 3-7.
Three-dimensional transvaginal sonography (3-D TVS) images of müllerian uterine anomalies in the coronal plane.
Below each are corresponding diagrammatic uteri and differing organizational definitions.
A. Bicornuate uterus.
This 3-D TVS rendered image demonstrates a concave external fundal contour that dips to a point near or below the interostial line (green line).
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Elysia Moschos.
B. Septate uterus.
This sonogram depicts the narrow angle between the two small endometrial cavities, which is characteristic of a septate) uterus.
The external contour here is flat but may show minor fundal indentation.
C. Arcuate uterus.
This image illustrates the normal external uterine contour and obtuse angle of the endometrial cleft that is characteristic of an arcuate uterus.
Organizations vary among their use of the terms intercornual, interostial, or interstitial line.
ASRM = American Society for Reproductive Medicine; ESHRE/ESGE = European Society of Human Reproduction and Embryology/European Society for Gynaecological Endoscopy.
Data from American Society for Reproductive Medicine, 2016, Bermejo, 2010, Grimbizis, 2013, 2016.
Bicornuate uterus carries increased risks for miscarriage, preterm birth, and
malpresentation (Chan, 2011a; Mastrolia, 2017).
As discussed in the prior section, rare surgical correction by metroplasty is reserved for highly selected cases.
Septate Uterus (Class V) With this anomaly, a resorption defect leads to a persistent complete or partial longitudinal uterine septum (see Fig. 3-5).
In the rare Robert uterus, an asymmetric longitudinal septum creates a sequestered noncommunicating hemicavity that acts similar to a rudimentary horn .
Many septate uteri are identified during evaluation of infertility or recurrent pregnancy loss.
Although an abnormality may be identified with HSG or 2-D TVS, typically 3-D TVS or MR imaging is required to differentiate septate and bicornuate uteri.
Experts still debate diagnostic criteria (see Fig. 3-7).
Septate anomalies can be associated with increased risks for adverse pregnancy outcomes that include miscarriage, preterm delivery, and malpresentation (Chan, 2011a; Ghi, 2012).
In those with recurrent pregnancy loss, hysteroscopic septal resection may improve birth rates (American Society for Reproductive Medicine, 2016; Corroenne, 2018; Valle, 2013).
During a subsequent labor, those with prior septal resection, especially if complicated by uterine perforation, carry a small risk for uterine rupture (Homer, 2000; Sentilhes, 2005).
Arcuate Uterus (Class VI) This malformation is a mild deviation from the normally developed uterus (see Fig. 3-7).
Most consider this anomaly benign, but some have found excessive second-trimester losses, preterm labor, and malpresentation (Chan, 2011a; Mucowski, 2010; Prior, 2018; Woelfer, 2001).
Cesarean Delivery As noted in the above sections, cesarean delivery rates are increased with müllerian uterine anomalies.
Data regarding subsequent trial of labor after cesarean (TOLAC) are few and show evidence both for and against its success and safety (Erez, 2007; Ravasia, 1999).
Failed TOLAC attempts or the risk of rupture may stem from smaller than normal cavity size, abnormal propagation of myometrial action potentials, and a weaker cesarean scar due to congenitally altered vascular anatomy .
Other factors that support or disfavor TOLAC are similar to those for women with normalshaped uteri and are outlined in Chapter 31.
In those without prior cesarean delivery, external cephalic version (ECV) is reasonable to avoid primary cesarean delivery for malpresentation.
A smaller uterine cavity or an obstructing midline partition may limit fetal turning.
These are added to the traditional list of factors that should be reviewed when assessing a potential ECV candidate .
At times, a müllerian anomaly may not be diagnosed until cesarean delivery, and additional information should be methodically sought.
Prior to hysterotomy closure, the cavity is manually explored to define the length of any cavity partition.
If a rudimentary horn is found, the main cavity is also digitally explored for a communication.
However, this may be missed due to its narrow caliber.
After closure, the fundus is examined.
The external contour is delineated to differentiate bicornuate from didelphys types.
If only one adnexum is found, a unicornuate uterus is suspected.
In this case, if an obvious rudiment is not attached to the main horn, the surgeon should trace the embryological migratory path of the paramesonephric duct starting at the patient’s back and sweeping forward.
If found, the rudiment may be removed or at minimum its accompanying fallopian tube should be ligated to prevent later ectopic pregnancy.
With any müllerian anomaly, both renal fossae are examined intraoperatively to confirm kidneys.
Postoperative radiologic assessment of the urinary collecting anatomy is reasonable.
Treatment with Cerclage Uterine anomalies are one risk for cervical insufficiency (Althuisius, 2001; Berghella, 1999; Mastrolia, 2018).
Some women with uterine anomalies and repetitive pregnancy loss after the first trimester may benefit from cervical cerclage (Golan, 1992; Yassaee, 2011).
Others with partial cervical atresia or hypoplasia also may benefit (Ludmir, 1991; Song,
2015). For women with a uterine anomaly, candidacy for cervical length sonographic screening or for cerclage placement is determined by the same criteria used for women without a uterine defect (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2021; Society for Maternal–Fetal Medicine, 2016).
These topics are discussed in Chapters 45 (p. 794) and 11 (p. 205), respectively.
# Diethylstilbestrol-related Abnormalities (Class VII).
In the 1960s, a synthetic nonsteroidal estrogen—diethylstilbestrol (DES)— was used to treat threatened abortion, preterm labor, preeclampsia, and diabetes.
It was remarkably ineffective.
Moreover, women exposed as fetuses carry increased risks for vaginal clear cell adenocarcinoma, cervical intraepithelial neoplasia, and vaginal adenosis (Hatch, 2001; Herbst, 1971; Robboy, 1984).
Women exposed in utero can also show a cervix or vagina with a transverse septum, circumferential ridge, or cervical collar.
Uteri are potentially smaller or have a T-shaped cavity (see Fig. 3-5) .
Women exposed as fetuses are now postreproductive, but they did suffer risks for infertility and adverse pregnancy outcome (Kaufman, 2000; Palmer, 2001).
# Fallopian Tube Abnormalities.
The fallopian tubes develop from the unpaired distal ends of the müllerian ducts.
Congenital anomalies include accessory ostia, complete or segmental tubal agenesis, and several embryonic cystic remnants.
The most common is a small, benign cyst attached by a pedicle to the distal end of the fallopian tube—the hydatid of Morgagni.
In other cases, benign paratubal cysts may be of mesonephric or mesothelial origin.
Last, in utero exposure to DES is associated with various tubal abnormalities .
Uterine Flexion.
Moderate flexion of the pregnant uterus is typically inconsequential, but exaggerated flexion may pose unique complications.
Anteflexion describes forward angling of the uterine fundus in the sagittal plane relative to the cervix.
In extreme cases, the fundus later in pregnancy falls forward to lie below the lower margin of the symphysis.
Abdominal wall laxity is contributory.
This uterine position can prevent proper transmission of labor contractions but is usually corrected by repositioning and application of an abdominal binder.
Retroflexion describes uterine fundal angling posteriorly in the sagittal plane.
A growing retroflexed uterus fundus will occasionally become trapped in the hollow of the sacrum .
Symptoms include pelvic pressure or pain plus voiding dysfunction or retention.
During bimanual pelvic examination, the cervix will be anterior and behind the symphysis pubis, whereas the uterus is wedged in the deep pelvis.
Sonography or MR imaging can aid diagnosis (Gardner, 2013; Grossenburg, 2011).
Figure 3-8.
A. With uterine incarceration, the uterus is wedged between the sacral promontory and symphysis pubis.
Resulting pressure against the urethra and rectum can cause urinary retention and constipation, respectively (Reproduced with permission from Corton MM: Anatomy.
In Yeomans ER, Hoffman BL, Gilstrap LC III, et al (eds): Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd ed.
New York, NY: McGraw Hill; 2017.
B. Sagittal transvaginal sonogram shows a first-trimester fetus and incarcerated uterine fundus.
The marked retroflexion brings the fundus to lie beneath the cervix.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Angela Seasley.
With continued uterine growth, the incarcerated uterus can spontaneously resolve over 1 to 2 weeks.
A knee-chest position assumed by the patient several times daily may assist resolution .
An indwelling urinary catheter or intermittent self-catheterization resolves retention.
Persistent cases require manual repositioning.
For this, after bladder catheterization, the uterus can usually be pushed out of the pelvis when the woman is placed in a knee-chest position.
Often, this is best accomplished by digital pressure applied through the rectum or vagina.
Intravenous sedation or spinal analgesia aids comfort and allows sufficient dislodging forces .
Afterward, insertion of a soft, space-filling
pessary for a few weeks usually prevents recurrence .
For rare resistant cases, advancing a colonoscope or colonoscopic insufflation can dislodge the fundus (Newell, 2014; Seubert, 1999).
Upward round ligament traction during laparoscopy also has been described .
Rarely, sacculation may form as an extensive lower uterine segment dilation due to persistent uterine entrapment.
Clinically, the elongated vagina extends above the level of the deeply descended fetal head.
The Foley catheter is frequently palpated above the level of the umbilicus!
In these extreme cases, sonography and MR imaging help define anatomy (Gottschalk, 2008; Lee, 2008).
To avoid uterine rupture, cesarean delivery is necessary when sacculation is marked.
Spearing (1978) recommended extending the abdominal incision above the umbilicus and delivering the entire uterus from the abdomen before hysterotomy.
Correct anatomical relationships are ideally restored to help prevent inadvertent incisions into and through the vagina and bladder .
Singh, 2007; Uma, 2002).
Figure 3-9.
With anterior sacculation, note the markedly attenuated anterior uterine wall and atypical location of the true uterine fundus.
Uterine torsion is another rare acquired anomaly.
During pregnancy, the uterus commonly rotates gently to the maternal right.
Rotation exceeding 180 degrees creates torsion, and most cases stem from uterine leiomyomas, müllerian anomalies, fetal malpresentation, pelvic adhesions, or laxity of the abdominal wall or uterine ligaments.
In one review of 212 cases, associated symptoms were obstructed labor, intestinal or urinary complaints, abdominal pain, uterine hypertonus, vaginal bleeding, or hypotension .
In some women, torsion can be confirmed preoperatively with MR imaging, which shows a twisted vagina that appears X-shaped rather than its normal H-shape .
Flipped placenta location and abnormal umbilical Doppler findings have been described sonographically .
However, uterine torsion is usually found at the time of cesarean delivery, and the severely rotated uterus should be repositioned anatomically before hysterotomy.
In some cases, an inability to reposition or a failure to recognize the torsion may lead to a posterior hysterotomy incision (Albayrak, 2011; Karavani, 2017).
Rotation of 90 degrees risks uterine vessel laceration .